<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ormonds curtain drawn. In a short discourse concerning Ireland; wherein his treasons, and the corruption of his instruments are laid bare to the stroke of justice.</title>
            <author>Temple, John, Sir, 1600-1677.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T631</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E513_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R205632</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864953</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864953</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95615)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 80:E513[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ormonds curtain drawn. In a short discourse concerning Ireland; wherein his treasons, and the corruption of his instruments are laid bare to the stroke of justice.</title>
                  <author>Temple, John, Sir, 1600-1677.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32+ p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Ends on p. 32 with catchword: ample.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "By Sr John Temple; but not finished: [S. Gellibrand]"; "8ber [i.e. October] 5. 1646".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ormonde, James Butler, --  Duke of, 1610-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:117186:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>ORMONDS</hi> CVRTAIN DRAWN: In a ſhort Diſcourſe concerning <hi>Ireland;</hi> Wherein his Treaſons, and the corruption of his Inſtruments are laid bare to the ſtroke of JUSTICE.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>IVILIS, <hi>a perſon of reputation, having in London met with</hi> DECIUS (<hi>a Gentleman of</hi> Ireland, <hi>and former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of his moſt intimate acquaintance</hi>) <hi>being not ſatisfied with one ſingle ſight of him, having long thought he had ſuffered with thoſe many thouſands of</hi> Engliſh <hi>that were destroyed by that bloody Rebellion; deſired him if his lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure would permit, to goe along with him to his houſe in</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>where he might learne of him, how it had fared with him, ſince he had laſt the happineſſe to ſee him, and what occaſions drew him into this Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>DECIUS <hi>accepting of the invitation, and by the way as they went, accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his ill fortune that had brought him to the firſt ſight of him by chance: And</hi> CIVILIS <hi>(according to his wonted manner) returning his civility with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt; they arrived at the place which</hi> CIVILIS <hi>called his owne: And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing entred, and having ſate ſome while together,</hi> MARCUS <hi>a Gentleman of quality, and friend to</hi> CIVILIS, <hi>comes in to them; who (thinking they were private) would have as ſoon retired, had not his friend called to him, and invited him to ſit downe by them, and then ſpake to him after this manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Gentleman pointing to <hi>Decius,</hi> being lately come out of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Civilis.</note> and one whom (for the particular friendſhip between us) I thought I might be bold with: having done me the favour to come ſo far out of his way as to this houſe; I was curious to enquire of him the condition of affaires in that Kingdome: And having newly begun to informe me as you came in, I am ſure I ſhall not wrong you, if I deſire you to partake with me; and I hope I ſhall treſpaſſe
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117186:2"/>as little upon my friend, in deſiring him to proceed in his relation, ſeeing by your arrivall he ſhall have one witneſſe more of his skill in Elocution. MARCUS <hi>thanking his friend</hi> CIVILIS <hi>for the favour he had done him: And both of them ſtrengthning each others perſwaſions, that</hi> DECIUS <hi>would take that paines upon him: He ſpake to this purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though my imperfections might in ſome meaſure excuſe my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> and the ſadneſſe of thoſe things I have both ſeen and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, might affright me from the remembrance of them: I ſhall rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily overlook my ſelf, and apply me to fulfill your commands, where the pleaſure I ſhall receive in obeying of you, may counterpoiſe all inconveniences whatſoever. You may remember CIVILIS (as this Gentleman came in to us) I was telling of you, How happily the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were every where ſeated in <hi>Ireland,</hi> how they were ſpread and ſowne in all parts of the Kingdome; how the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were every day obliged and enriched by them, and brought by their converſe with them to a greater degree of civility then they were thought capable of; and (to make the happineſſe of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſeem compleat) what hopes they had conceived, and what ſure grounds they had built their confidence upon, of a laſtingneſſe and ſtability in that their good condition: I doubt not but you will pardon me this fault, if (not to hold you long) I proceed wher I left off, and not go backward to the particulars I then mentioned. CIVILIS <hi>and</hi> MARCUS <hi>both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to eaſe him of ſo much trouble;</hi> DECIUS <hi>continued his ſpeech as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the beginning of that bloody Maſſacre (which I hope for ever will be remembred, to the ſhame of thoſe that were the Authors and contrivers of it, as well of the actors, and the glory of that God, who by ſparing us a remnant, has kept us from being like <hi>Sodom,</hi> and being made like unto <hi>Gomorrah:</hi>) at the beginning (I ſay) of that moſt horrid Rebellion, I was at my owne houſe in the Country, ſome threeſcore miles from <hi>Dublin;</hi> where (I may ſay without boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) I enjoyed my ſhare of the comfort which God beſtowed upon me, in common with the reſt of my brethren over the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>For ſeven or eight miles round the place where I lived, the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants were all <hi>Engliſh</hi> and good Proteſtants, ſo that that place might with more right then the other, have beene called the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Pale;</hi> me thought it was the onely place (if any) out of which Saint <hi>Patricke</hi> had baniſhed all venomous creatures; for the reſt of the Kingdome, we have found he onely took the poyſon out of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117186:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>the earth to plant it in the Natives (as our Saviour gave leave to the Devils (having caſt them out of the man) to enter into the Swine.) Whilſt we lived in this happy condition (as we eſteemed it) my little fortune (as generally that of the whole <hi>Engliſh</hi> over all the Kingdome,) being never in ſo good a poſture, and with Gods bleſſing, every day more then other encreaſing upon our hands. On that never to be forgotten three and twentieth of <hi>October,</hi> when we were (as it were) buried in ſecurity, and thought of no ill, either of doing it to others, or receiving it from them, eſpecially from the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> (who we thought were tyed too faſt by the many favours and curteſies of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> conſtantly and without wearineſſe done to them) to caſt thoſe pleaſant cords behind their backs, and to embrew their hands in the blood of thoſe that had filled thoſe ſame hands with ſo many and good deeds. Truly Sirs, as often as I think of it, I am almoſt out of my ſelfe, and ſtand amazed at the depth of that wickedneſſe, that reached deeper then hell it ſelfe, at which the very Prince of the Divels could not but be aſtoniſhed, being out-done in his owne trade (though he were a murtherer even from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.) Whilſt, I ſay, we were in this pleaſant ſleep, we were ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly awaked with the noyſe of warre, or rather, with the hideous out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryes of our poor Neighbours, who in vaine poured out their breath to preſerve their lives. Alas poore creatures, they thought they had to doe with ſuch as themſelves (whoſe eares were never ſhut to any that called to them in their miſery) but they were in the pawes of Lyons and Tygars, or what is worſe, they were in the hands of Wild Men (if I may call them men.) The fleſh of the Proteſtants might poſſibly turne the edge of their ſwords and skeines, but it was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for their prayers or teares to turne their hearts. You have read of the Savage Canibals in the <hi>Indies,</hi> that having taken their enemies in battle, delight to beſmeare their bodies and faces in their blood; and having eaten their fleſh, carry about their armes and legs upon their ſhoulders in triumph: In that poſture (having bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barouſly Ravaged up and downe the Country) and wearied, rather then ſatisfied themſelves with killing) with their hands and weapons dropping wet in the blood (not of their enemies taken in battle, but of their neighbours and friends ſurprized aſleep, or at their honeſt labour) they entred my houſe, and having ſacrificed my two ſonnes, who were the firſt they met with to their accurſed fury, they ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſackt every corner at their pleaſure without fear of reſiſtance, having before ſlaine my men-ſervants in the field, when they expected no ſuch wages: My Wife, three other children and my ſelfe, ſought out a place to hide us in, but all in vaine, for we were ſoon found out,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117186:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and having ſtripped us as naked as by this time they had made every room in the houſe, they brought us into a field hard by, and joyned us to a great company of other afflicted ſoules, whom they had ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the ſame barbarous manner, and (that there might be variety in their miſchiefe) reſerved for a more lingring end: It was then in the extremity of a winter, that for ſharpnes and cold, had not its like in many yeers before in that Kingdome. I ſhall forbeare both for your ſakes and my own, to ſet before you the lamentable complaints and the dying groanes of many a poore ſoule that (as we were hur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried up and downe to be witneſſes of their barbarous cruelties infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted upon many thouſands) through the extremity of the weather, were ſtarved to death; amongſt whom, my three children (the eldeſt not above eight yeers old) gave up their laſt breath in the armes of their almoſt dying Mother.</p>
            <p>I have ſo ſharp a feeling of the miſery which you could not chooſe but ſuffer,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> being in this condition, that I long impatiently to be freed from the torment I endure in your particular; I pray you therefore make what haſte you can to bring me out of it, by letting us know how at length you eſcaped thoſe ſo great dangers; for indeed I can hardly yet beleeve you are ſafe (though I ſee you here) unleſſe you tell me you are ſo.</p>
            <p>I cannot but thank you for your fellow-feeling of my ſufferings,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> and to free you from the torment you are pleaſed to ſay you endure, I ſhall paſſe over thoſe monſtrous, unheard of cruelties which I ſaw with theſe eyes, whilſt I was carried about from place to place, with many hundreds more of my brethren, who drank all of the ſame cup with me: and I am induced the rather to doe it, in regard there are ſo many who have given large and true Relations of them, whoſe paines therein may appeare to after Ages, like ſo may Night pieces amongſt the Monuments of this Nation: And I hope will be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved by all, though in themſelves almoſt incredible; and though many doe their endeavour to caſt a vaile over them.</p>
            <p>The evidences of their cruelties are ſo many and cleer,<note place="margin">Marcus.</note> that I think there is none ſo ignorant that is not acquainted with them, and none (I preſume) will doubt of them, but ſuch as inwardly wiſh they had been greater; and yet I confeſſe there are many even amongſt our ſelves, that are not afraid to tinter their charity, ſo farre as to think they would not have done what they did but upon urging and preſſing neceſſity:<note n="a" place="margin">Biſhop of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſory</hi> his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery of My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries.</note> 
               <hi>That they poor people for feare of their Religion and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing driven our of the Kingdome were forced to doe what they did.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That our adverſaries ſhould daub over the matter ſo,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> were a thing only to be admired, by ſuch as think the action ſo glorious &amp; beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117186:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>that it needs no art or paint to ſet it off; but that ſuch as profeſſe the Proteſtant Religion ſhould make uſe of ſo monſtrous and vile a colour, and labour to lay an imputation upon their friends to acquit their adverſaries, is a thing not at firſt fight to be underſtood, and may very well ſtumble an honeſt man, did he not looke more neerly as well into the men as their doctrine, I ſhall not trouble my ſelfe or you to confute ſo malicious an imputation, being as ſufficiently knowne to be falſe, as it renders the Authors corrupt and ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous.</p>
            <p>When I mentioned that ſaying of thoſe men,<note place="margin">Marcus.</note> I did it not to ground any opinion of my owne upon it; when I firſt heard of it, (Ile aſſure you) it moved not ſo much my beliefe as my admiration, and thefore you may well ſpare your confutation of it, 'tis enough but to repeat it. I could not ſee in my weak reaſon what feare they could conceive of a deſigne to root out their Religion by force, when I knew the conſtant opinion of all Proteſtants in all Ages, abjured violence in matter of faith, as a thing worthy onely of the Whore of <hi>Rome,</hi> who ſhall be deſtroyed (if ever) by the breath of Gods mouth, that is, by the preaching of the Word, and not by drawing of the Sword: Beſides this, I remembred it was a charge againſt the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of that Kingdome, that they connived too much at the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe and encreaſe of Popery there, ſo that they could have no cauſe of feare from any thing done againſt them at that time: And for the Parliament after, they never (before that Rebellion) deſired more either here or there, then the execution of the Lawes which were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready in force againſt them; from which they ought not to free themſelves by the ſword, or a generall Maſſacre: And for that other part of the excuſe, or rather accuſation concerning their eſtates, that they were forced to take that courſe, leaſt they might have been rooted out: If there were any grievances by Miniſters, the way for redreſſe was open, and they might have been their owne Judges; the Parliament then ſitting at <hi>Dublin,</hi> wherein they themſelves had the ſwaying vote, and might have done themſelves the higheſt right that could be deſired; ſo that I could not ſee how they had any thing to feare on this ſide either: Beſides all this, I have heard that imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately before the breaking out of the Rebellion, they had many graces afforded to them by the King, which might have ſecured them for ever from the thought of the leaſt oppreſſion.</p>
            <p>You ſay right Sir,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> there were many graces (as they called them) beſtowed on them, and ſuch, as (for their largeneſſe) were very much wondred at by all that wiſhed well to the good of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in that Kingdome. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> in thoſe graces had neere upon a third part
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117186:4"/>of the Kingdome freely granted to them, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> wholly ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from having any Plantations therein: Which Lands (if they had been managed as was deſigned, and by right ſhould have been) beſides the ſecurity which thereby would have redounded to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> being the beſt meanes under God to have ſetled that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in perpetuall Peace, Religion and Civility: His Majeſties Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues would have been bettered out of thoſe lands by 90000<hi rend="sup">lib</hi>. <hi>per Annum,</hi> and that upon a very moderate eſtimate, allowing about ten pence for every acre; thoſe Territories being by admeaſurement, knowne to be above two millions of acres, beſides the caſuall Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues which would enſue: This you may well ſay was a Princely gift indeed. But beſides this, there were many other things granted to them at the ſame time; for what reaſon I will not ſay, but ſure I am to the utter undoing of the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> Which (if they had but ſtayed nine dayes longer from the execution of their Treaſon, till the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, according to the prorogation ſhould have met againe at <hi>Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi>) had been confirmed to them by a Law: but there was ſomething more in the wind then their owne benefit, that made them haſten it ſo much.</p>
            <p>We underſtand your meaning,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> and I for my part am very much of your mind: I have heard all the particulars of thoſe graces, and doe not ſee how they could think of making better conditions to themſelves by a warre, then they had therein already granted to them, ſuppoſing the fortune of the game ſhould leane on their ſide: This being ſo, I cannot ſee what the leaſt appearance of reaſon there can be in that colour, <hi>That the Iriſh were neceſſitated to doe what they did.</hi> I have alwayes thought upon what I have heard and read; that if there were at any time any fault in the government of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, it was in the gentleneſſe and remiſneſſe of it, in letting the curſed ſeed not onely live, but encreaſe, even to an hundred fold: The <hi>Iriſh</hi> according to my obſervation, are a people not to be ruled but with a rod of iron: <hi>Aut ſerviunt humiliter, aut ſuperbe dominantur,</hi> was of old a good Character of their natures, which they have kept to this very day, being to be compared to nothing more fitly then to thoſe two heady elements of fire and water, that are the beſt ſervants being kept within their own bounds; but once maſters, lay all waſte before them; this the Romans even of old obſerved very well of them, when<note n="b" place="margin">Agricol. in Ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</note> one of them undertook to maintaine that Kingdome in good ſubjection to the Roman Empire (which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver yet compaſſe) <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na legione &amp; modicis Auxiliis ſi Romana ubique Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma &amp; libertas quaſie conſpectu Tolleretur:</hi> And I cannot find a greater cauſe of this (I hope the laſt) and of thoſe many other inſurrections
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117186:4"/>againſt the <hi>Engliſh</hi> upon all occaſions, then <hi>the ſmoothing of all former Rebellions by Pardons upon fained ſubmiſſions,</hi> whereby the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to play childrens play, and runne in and out at their plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and had ſtill opportunity to better and mend their new trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in poynt of execution, as they found they were out, and failed in their old: As if the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> when they made but one or two of the principall actors examples, had cut off but ſo many <hi>Hidra's</hi> heads which alwayes multiplied upon their hands; they alwayes skin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned over the wound before they had ſearched and drawne it to the quick; ſo that the ill humour brake out continually, not long after in a worſe manner: and that which at firſt was but the corruption of one inconſiderable part, for want of cutting that off, grew to a Gan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>green, that often heretofore, but never ſo apparently as at this day, endangered the whole body.</p>
            <p>CIVILIS <hi>had proceeded further, had not his friend</hi> MARCUS <hi>mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily pulled him by the ſleeve, and told him he forgot himſelfe, ſince his Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary had long ſince laid downe the cudgell, and the onely ground of the digreſſion was blowne away with the firſt breath:</hi> CIVILIS <hi>thanking his friend for his feaſonable remembrance, deſired</hi> DECIUS <hi>to take up his Relation where he left off: which he (being loth to deprive himſelfe of the content he received in bearing of him on that ſubject) hardly conſented to; but</hi> MARCUS <hi>interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, he proceeded as followes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You left me in very ill company, and ſo you muſt find me:<note place="margin">Decius.</note> I and my Wife for many days together, having, as I told you, nothing to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our nakedneſſe, but what we could gather up in the way, and as little to fill our bellies; but (in the condition we were in) hunger was the leaſt part of our torment, for we were ſo little uſed to meat, that we had hardly room to receive any. We were driven thus, for many dayes, from place to place, like ſheep appointed for the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; and they that had not the ſtrength to goe as faſt as thoſe cruell villaines would have them, had the good fortune that many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand others wanted, to be buried in the next bogpit or ditch they met with: When they thought they had ſufficiently loaden us with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and indeed compleated their cruelties, being not able to doe any more (or rather God not ſuffering of them) they permitted us (in their more cruell mercy) to take our fortunes, beleeving we could not poſſibly eſcape the hands of other their companions, who would have been glad of ſuch ſubjects for their cruelty to work on. Having thus cleered their hands of us, and, as they thought, decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the deceiver, we made what ſhift we could, and having loſt much
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117186:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>of our company in the ſnow, who were able to goe no farther, and having overtaken many more that had ſet out from other parts, in the ſame ſad journey with us, and not in any better condition: We at length, by Gods great mercy, arrived ſafe at the next ſtrength to us, which at this time was poſſeſſed by the <hi>Engliſh:</hi> Where after we had refreſhed our ſelves as well as the charity of wel-affected people would permit, being divided amongſt ſo many as daily reſorted thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the like neſſity: That place being too little to containe us, we ſet forward, not without great danger, to <hi>Dublin;</hi> where as ſoon as we were arrived, my Wife, by reaſon of the extremity of the cold ſhe had taken, and the griefe ſhe conceived for the loſſe of her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and what elſe could be deare to her in this world, fell ſick and dyed, and multitudes more of thoſe that got ſafe to <hi>Dublin,</hi> having not time, as it were, to dye before; or the varieties of deaths that ſtared them in the faces, being not able before now to agree, which ſhould take poſſeſſion of them. When they were come thither, and conſidered the great misfortunes, but more the heavy hand of God upon the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> their hearts brake in ſunder, and I am confident the blood of many thouſands who have dyed ſince, and will doe for theſe many yeers yet to come, in that and other places of that and this Kingdome, whether they fled for refuge and ſanctuary, will be put upon the ſame ſcore, and their number I think may amount to as many as fell by the ſword.</p>
            <p>CIVILIS <hi>and</hi> MARCUS <hi>being both ſtruck with amazement at the horridneſſe of theſe things they had heard, could not readily find the uſe of their tongues to expreſſe the fulneſſe of their hearts: At length</hi> CIVILLS <hi>having walked a turn or two in the room, and being returned to himſelf, as from a dream, firſt vented his thoughts in this manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My good friend,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> though I am unſpeakably grieved for your great ſufferings, your owne ſafety does not a little abate my ſorrow: I never look upon that damned Maſter-piece of the Devil, but, that in my owne thoughts I am ready to excuſe all the curſed trecheries that ever I heard or read of, compared to this, me thinks they look but like ſo many <hi>Piaefraudes,</hi> and the torments of all paſt ages may be thought to have proceeded more from the favourable mercies of men, then from their cruelty: I am confident that God that has ſo preſerved you, has done it partly for this end, that your owne eyes might behold the Vyals of his wrath and vengeance which he has filled and laid up in ſtore, plentifully poured out uon them: and I am perſwaded if we can but with patience expect his owne time, the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117186:5"/>time will come, and your eyes ſhall ſee it, when thoſe tongues that cryed ſo loud in the day of <hi>Jeruſalem, Race it, raee it, even to the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſhall cry as loud (but all in vaine) to thoſe ſame mountaines whereon you were ſcattered and hunted like Partridges, to fall and cover them; and thoſe hands that have laine ſo heavy on the backs of ſo many thouſands of you, ſhall ſtrike as hard their owne breſts, and cleave as faſt to their owne loynes; and thoſe feet that have been ſo ſwift to ſhed blood, ſhall not carry them away ſo faſt, but that the fierce anger of the Lord ſhall overtake them.</p>
            <p>Though I cannot be ſo eloquent as my friend CIVILIS,<note place="margin">Marcus.</note> yet my <hi>Amen</hi> may very well ſtand at the end of his ſpeech: <hi>So let thine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies periſh, O Lord, and thoſe that hate thee flee before thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I perceive MARCUS that the ſad Relation which you have new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heard, has not wrought ſo kindly with you,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> as it has done with me, ſince you can ſo ſoon abuſe your friend; but I will beare it for once, if you promiſe me to be content with our company all this evening; and you DECIUS will be pleaſed (I hope) to beare part of his burden. Both being well ſatisfied, CIVILIS <hi>turning to</hi> DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIUS, <hi>ſpake to this purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since you have been pleaſed to trouble your ſelfe thus farre, give me leave to diſturb you a little more, and to know how long you have been in this Kingdome, and what occaſions brought you out of <hi>Ireland:</hi> I doubt not but you will excuſe me, knowing how particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar an intereſt my affection gives me in every thing that concernes you; and I know MARCUS will take it for the beſt part of his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment in this houſe, to ſit and heare you. MARCUS <hi>agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to what was ſaid for him, he ſate downe by</hi> CIVILIS, <hi>and</hi> DECIUS <hi>ſpake as followes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You cannot deſire that of me which I ſhall not be ready to grant you; you muſt know then, that at my firſt coming to <hi>Dublin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Decius.</note> I found the City in great perplexity, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> not knowing which they ſhould feare firſt, either the <hi>Iriſh</hi> without, or thoſe within amongſt themſelves; they were all, as it were, at their wits ends, and no bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy almoſt knew which way to turne himſelfe: The Rebels were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite for numbers, and within the City, onely a poore company of raw ignorant Townſmen, that for their number could not be thought able to conquer ſo often as their enemies might be overcome: Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all theſe diſcouragements, though I ſaw paleneſſe in every mans face, each one accounting himſelfe already (as it were) amongſt the dead: I obſerved ſo much courage and reſolution in thoſe that then ſate at the <hi>Helme,</hi> that I for my part could not at all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117186:6"/>feare a ſhipwrack; and therefore at that time could not think of quitting the Kidgdome, though I ſaw many take that courſe as the ſafeſt, hazarding themſelves in a ſtorm at Sea in open Botes, to ſcape that they feared on Land, if they ſhould ſtay behind: Thoſe that onely attended the ſervice, and were carefull to diſcharge their du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, though with the apparent danger of their lives, by ſitting con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly at Counſell-Board, whither multitudes of ſuch as were then ſecret, and afterwards profeſſed Rebels, daily reſorted, and might (if God had not ſtayed their hands) have put their plot in execution for many weeks after their three and twentieth of <hi>October,</hi> as well as they could have done at that day. Thoſe, I ſay, that in al that foul weather (when the Heavens were all blackk about them, and not ſo much as one beame of comfort to be ſeen) ſtood ſtill to their tackling, and plyed their work, without ever giving over, were onely the two Lords Juſtices, by name, Sir <hi>William Parions</hi> and Sir <hi>John Bortaſe,</hi> and Sir <hi>Adam Lofius,</hi> Vice-treaſurer; Sir <hi>John Temple,</hi> Maſter of the Rolls, Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> from the time that he arrived at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and when he was not abroad in the Field; and Sir <hi>Robert Meredith,</hi> Chancellour of the Exchequer: Thoſe other blazing-ſtarres and unlucky meteors that have ſince hung over our heads, and have had ſuch ill influence on all the affaires of that Kingdome, and put all into combuſtion, being ſome of them at that time not exhaled from the earth, &amp; as lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle known by name of Privy-Counſellours as they deſerved it; and others, ſome for feare, and ſome for diſ-affection to the ſervice, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves at home, and ſeldome or never comming to Counſell or having fled into <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the great mercy of God,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> that a that time of extream ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard and neceſſity, ſent you ſuch men as were not afraid to ſtand for you, and to open their mouths in your defence, when yours and their enemies fiſts were ready to encloſe them with a blow; and tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ought to be had in everlaſting remembrance: and thoſe that abſenced themſelves in that time of preſſing neceſſity (by my conſent) ſhould have had the Counſell-chamber-doores for ever ſhut in their faces &amp; I can as little excuſe thoſe that kept themſelves away through feare, as thoſe others that did it through diſ-affection, it being a breach of truſt in both; and he that feares even his life, when his Religion and Country cals for, and requires his help, will to ſave his life, or perhaps a poorer commodity, betray both.</p>
            <p>We have found what you ſay very true, and could have wiſhed that they that kept themſelves then away, ahd done ſo ſtill, and not to have come to doe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> the greateſt miſchiefe inſtead of ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. But if you pleaſe I ſhall proceed.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:117186:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> You will doe us a ſpeciall favour in it.<note place="margin">Civilis. Decius.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Charles Coot</hi> (by a ſpeciall providence being ſent to <hi>Dublin</hi> when the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſtood in ſo much need of a man of his ſpirits (was imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately made Governour of that City; how he carried himſelfe in that charge, and what reſolution and gallantry he ſhewed in the field againſt the Rebels, with that ſmall handfull of men which the State put under his command: If I were able to expreſſe to you, I might very well be thought to ſpeak a piece of a <hi>Romanſe:</hi> It ſhall ſuffice that I tell you, that by his couragious execution, and the as faithfull contrivement of thoſe that ſate at Counſell-board (the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of God accompanying their endeavours) whereas at firſt for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (with all their ſtrength) to march out of the City as farre as <hi>Clantarfe,</hi> a place not two miles from them,<note place="margin">The Counſell onely.</note> was looked upon as an attempt of great hazard and danger; in a very ſhort time we were able to ſeek the Rebels in their owne holds, and beat them, as I may ſay, on their owue Dunghils. Not long after this, the Army that was ſent from hence by the Parliament, arrived ſafe at <hi>Dublin,</hi> which put new life and ſpirit into our breaſts, and as much terrified the Rebels, having its more then probable, ſome pre-aſſurance, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be done againſt them heer; thinking the troubles heere, being indeed a thread of the ſame ſpinning, would have followed their needle; but they were ſomewhat deceived in the time, though for the matter it fell out as was deſigned. The affaires of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants began now to ſmile upon them, and we perceived already the glimmerings of a more glorious day then ever we ſaw before (ſo that we were brought (if not to forget our former ſufferings, yet) at leaſt not to regard them, in compariſon of thoſe happy times we ſaw euery day drawing nearer and nearer to us; our Armies alwayes carried victory in their <hi>Van,</hi> and in their <hi>Reare,</hi> left the Country to the peaceable poſſeſſion of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> the Rebels running continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly before us; five chaſing a hundred, and ten putting a thouſand to flight.</p>
            <p>The reſolutions of the Counſell were apparently to the good of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and nothing to be ſeen amongſt them that favoured of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt or ſelfith ends: As we enjoyed the benefits of their labours and watchings, ſo we did our endeavours that they might be the better for our prayers, wherein we were not wanting, nor in the prayſes of our God for them, and the bleſſing, we daily received by their means that God that had compaſſion on us in our low eſtate, and when we were truly in our blood, ſaid unto us, Live.</p>
            <p>CIVIL IS <hi>and</hi> MARCUS <hi>being both as much affected with joy by this laſt part of</hi> DECIUS <hi>his Relation, as before they were with ſorrow;</hi> MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CUS
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117186:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>being not able any longer to containe himſelfe, interrupted</hi> DECIUS, <hi>as be was going on, and ſaid:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When I compare the firſt part of your Relation with this that you are now upon,<note place="margin">Marcus.</note> and conſider that Chaos and confuſion, that dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that was upon the face of the whole Land, and now againe, this light that was divided from that darkneſſe; me thinks I ſee the hand of God, like that of a man in it, and writing, as it did once to <hi>Belſhazzar,</hi> upon the wall; but mercy inſtead of judgement: Not as there,<note place="margin">Dan. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 42.8.</note> 
               <hi>Thy Kingdome is divided, and given to the Meads and Perſians;</hi> but this, <hi>My glory will I not give to another, nor my prayſe to graven Images.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas Sir,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> this evening and morning that you have ſeen, make but up the firſt day; there are ſix more behind, all dayes of labour and ſorrow to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and no Sabbath of reſt from their ſufferings. You have ſeen us, like a ſhip toſſed and driven to and fro in a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſtorme, our maſts ſplit, our ſailes blowne away, our anchors loſt, and in a word, left as men without hope in the world: you have ſeen us againe by the skilfull conduct of our Pilots, and the good providence of our great Maſter in Heaven, brought within ſight of a ſafe harbour, and now you muſt behold us ſplit upon the Bars mouth and every one like <hi>Pauls</hi> Paſſengers, ſome upon boards, and ſome upon broken pieces of the ſhippe, labouring to eſcape ſafely to Land.</p>
            <p>CIVILIS <hi>deſiring him to let them partake with him both of the good and had,</hi> DECIUS <hi>continued his ſpeech as followes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt appearance, and (as I may ſay) the buds that have ſince bloſſomed and growne into ſuch bitter and uncomfortable fruits, were ſeen after the death of that never to be forgotten, incomparable Commander, Sir <hi>Charles Coot;</hi> a death that was attended with as much ſorrow, and proſecuted with as much miſery to us, as it will be remembred with glory and honour to him.</p>
            <p>Wee in theſe parts were not a little ſenſible of your great loſſe in a man that was every way ſo fitted for thoſe times (if it had been Gods will they ſhould be mended) and though the manner of his fall (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vilie.</note> as is reported, by one of his Souldiers) did encreaſe the ſorrow of ſome; for my part, that circumſtance did not then work a greater griefe (ſeeing his enemies had not that happineſſe they deſired) as now (upon what you have told us) it has raiſed a ſuſpition in me, that there was ſomething more then faire play in the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117186:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> If it were ſo,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> God in the end will ſearch it out; and when all thoſe loud cryes of the Proteſtant blood in <hi>Ireland</hi> ſhall come before him, he will not turne away his eare from this: Whether it were ſo or no, I am ſure the party that did the deed was never queſtioned or exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned concerning the ſame; and there was ſo good uſe made of his death, as may make a man beleeve he was taken out of the way; that the Myſtery of that Iniquity which had a ſecret working in his life time, might be more fully revealed after his death: From that time every thing began to look new, and the Counſell-Board to be ſilled with new Counſellours; men that had laine hid before like Swal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes in winter; but now like Tares (ſowne by the wicked one) ſuddenly over-top the good Corne; ſo that there was to be ſeen an univerſall change in all our Counſels: as before our Counſellours looked all like Cherubims, face to face, you might ſee them now like <hi>Samp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ons</hi> Foxes, drawing ſeverall wayes: the former being too honeſt, to hold their tongues and ſuffer things, to run on quietly in diſorder; and theſe latter too numerous, and falſe to be over-ruled, from whence aroſe a ſlack and unfaithfull proſecution of the Warre, ſo well begun againſt the Rebels; the countenancing of all manner of unheard of confuſions, and the oppreſſion of the ſmall remainder of the almoſt heart-broken <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the bold and open favouring of the moſt bloody wretches that ever the Sun beheld. The labours of this Party and their diligence was ſo great, that within a ſhort time we were reduced to our firſt principles, and brought, as I may ſay, to a worſe condition (notwithſtanding the large and good ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies ſent from hence) then we were at the very beginning of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, when we had nothing almoſt (God knowes) to ſupport us. The place which God of his great mercy reſerved for a City of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to find ſafety and comfort in, was open and free to the worſt of their enemies, and they that had ſhed and poured out like waters, ſo much innocent blood in the Country, had the liberty to come thither, and profeſſe not their repentance, but their ſotrow that they did no more, though indeed that lay not in their power to commit greater villanies.</p>
            <p>As long as I lived in <hi>Dublin</hi> (I meane ſince the command of this Party) I could never learne that ever any true hearted proteſtant was relieved, or had even ordinary juſtice done him, if the caſe lay be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man, or a Papiſt. The affliction of my bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren being ſo great, and the tyranny under which they lived being ſo inſupportable, I choſe (rather then be a daily witneſſe of it, and in ſome meaſure a ſufferer, there being none, though never ſo poore, that could eſcape free) to quit all for the preſent, and bid adiew to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117186:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>that Kingdome, till it ſhould pleaſe God to look upon it in mercy, and ſettle juſtice and truth in the midſt of it; and this, I am ſure, was the thoughts and deſires of many thouſands <hi>Engliſh</hi> more, whoſe want of accommodation elſwhere keeps them in that place, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forces them to live in that intolerable ſlavery. And thus, with what brevity I could (fearing to be troubleſome) I have ſatisfied you concerning the occaſion of my comming into this Kingdome, where I have been theſe three moneths, moſt of which time I have ſpent in this City.</p>
            <p>We muſt acknowledge our ſelves much bound to you for the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour you have done us,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> and I hope ſince your comming to this place you are lightned of a good part of your burden, finding us in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, I preſume, farre beyond what you could imagine when you were in that Kingdome, and in a good way to a happy end, which will be (under God) the onely meanes to ſet you ſtreight againe in that Kingdme, whereof you are yet in capability: the Earle of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> having, notwithſtanding his Majeſties Letters, commanding him to conclude a peace there with the Rebels on any conditions; wiſely to this day held off his hand, as it is thought, from the very beginning, with an intention to give it to the Parliament. MAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CUS <hi>obſerving ſome confuſion in</hi> DECIUS <hi>his face upon this ſpeech, told his friend, that he feared he had ſpoken ſomething distatefull, and therefore that it concerned him, before be proceeded any further, to give</hi> DECIUS <hi>ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, who he ſaw was ſuddenly moved with ſomething that fell from him.</hi> CIVILIS <hi>thanking his friend, and deſiring</hi> DECIUS <hi>to be free with him, and to ſet him ſtraight, if he had failed, as he confeſſed he might very eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly doe, being not ſo well acquainted with the particulars of that Kingdome:</hi> DECIUS <hi>expreſſing ſome unwillingneſſe, and a kind of anger againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that his countenance had betrayed him, ſpake to this purpoſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhould be very 10th CIVILIS to diſcent from you in any thing but on neceſſary grounds,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> eſpecially in ſuch a buſineſſe as this that we are now fallen upon, which concernes a particular perſon, having, as you might have obſerved from the beginning of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, baulkt the mentioning of any perſon, as the actors in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, more then in the generall, knowing how ſubject it is (if we ſpeak ſharply, though accordin gto truth, in every particular) to the judgment and doome of paſſion, rancor and invectiveneſſe; yet fince a ſpeciall providence has brought the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> and laid him croſſe my way, I cannot paſſe him by without labouring to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you in the opinion you have conceived of him, and ſo farre am I from any private ſpleen or intereſt to draw me aſide to an obliquity
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117186:8"/>in what I ſhall lay before you; that I proteſt I heartily with I could with truth give my ſelfe the lye in what I ſhall ſay concerning him; I perceive by that little you have ſaid of him, how much you will wonder when I ſhall tell you, he has been the chiefe inſtrument of all the miſery that at this day the Proteſtants of that Kingdome groane under, and the moſt faithfull ſervant to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> that ever they had, wherein I muſt ſay, he has done but what his blood and nature re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him; his Family having long ſince degenerated into <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and for himſelfe in his owne inclination, one as much addicted to their wayes (having all his kinred and friends amongſt them) as he that knowes the leaſt either of Religion or humanity: And for that particular of keeping back the peace, I can aſſure you they deceive themſelves very much, that the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> would leave any thing undone that might tend to the perfecting of that work he has alwayes ſo vigorouſly purſued: Beleeve it Sir, that the peace there was not long ſince concluded (though I cannot poſitively ſay it is not at this day) was not becauſe the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> was unwilling to conſent to whatever the Rebels could demand of him, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary plainly appearing by thoſe Articles formerly conſented unto by him, (which I doubt not you have ſeen in print) wherein the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels have all they can deſire, both toleration of Religion, ſuſpention of Poynings Act, and all other Lawes made for the good of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants: But in truth, the obſtruction was ſtill on the Rebels ſide, they being unwilling) however they pretended otherwiſe) to accept of, or adventure on a peace; knowing how little (in the condition the King was) it could availe them, but alſo how thereby they ſhould be engaged to maintaine an Army here in <hi>England,</hi> whereby their owne Country might be left to the power of the Proteſtants (being conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in divers parts of the Kingdome;) and beſides, I doe verily beleeve they were conſcious to themelves of their owne inability to afford the King ſuch conſiderable aſſiſtance, as (after ſuch large con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions afforded to them) they would have been ſtrictly tyed unto, and his Majeſty might expect from them: However the Earle of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> and their other friends have repreſented them unto him as able to doe great matters.</p>
            <p>I cannot but much wonder indeed at what you tell us concerning the Earle of <hi>Ormond;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Civilis.</note> I doe remember him here in <hi>England</hi> under the care of <hi>Abbot</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and (for what I could diſcerne in his younger yeers) there appeared in him the hopes of better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances; and truly sir, I will not diſſemble with you, I have heard from many that are come from <hi>Dublin,</hi> and are ſtill in this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and on whom the Parliament has beſtowed ſome other marks of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117186:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>of their favour, beſides admitting of them to reſide here; that he has carried himſelfe from the beginning with all reſpect and good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and as one firmly rooted and reſolved in the proteſtant Religion.</p>
            <p>I doe not doubt but that you have met with many,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> who for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ends are engaged to ſpeak the beſt of him: Since my comming to this place, I happened more then once to be a witneſſe of ſome high expreſſions in his behalfe, but Ile aſſure you Sir, they came only from ſuch (as upon good grounds I was aſſured) were imployed over hither by the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> to work the people into a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate good opinion of him, that ſo he might continue his wicked practiſes againſt the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and that if at length the Proteſtant par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould prevaile in both Kingdomes (when there were no other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy to preſerve his eſtate, and to be able in time to come to doe further miſchiefe) he may on eaſier tearmes be accepted and make his peace: and I am perſwaded to this beliefe of theſe men, not onely by the falſneſſe of what ine very place they declaime, but alſo by the favour, I know, they are in with the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection he ſtill vouchſafes their commands, offices and intereſts there, notwithſtanding their reſiding heere, on pretences; which, if true, would render them extreamly odious to him: For the matter of what they give out, to hinder a harſher judgement of him concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iyg his education, and his firmneſſe in the Proteſtant Religion, I ſhall onely ſay this; that if you conſider the perverſneſſe of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of <hi>Iriſh,</hi> and more eſpecially of ſuch as have degenerated into them, Notwithſtanding the carefulleſt education, it will not ſeem impoſſible to you, though the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> notwithſtanding his breed under Biſhop <hi>Abbot,</hi> ſhould follow his kind, and prove as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious as any. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> of all people on the earth, are they that abhorre moſt to be reformed, in whoſe very being it is to love bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bariſme; and though ſometimes by peace, and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> dwelling amongſt them, they have ſeemed to caſt off their old skins, and put on ſome kind of civility upon the leaſt occaſion offered, they have run, like hogs, greedily againe to their vomits, and, like ſwine, have whet their tusks againſt ſuch as would onely have kept them from returning to wallow in the mire; and this is the reaſon that five or ſix hundred yeers have wrought ſo little upon them, and that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> have reaped onely the fruit of their labours, namely, the experience (and a very ſad one) how impoſſible a thing it is to make an unwilling Nation happy. And againe, if we look from the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> into the effects of it, and conſider this unnaturall Rebellion, we ſhall find that none are more cruelly bent againſt the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117186:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and thirſt more after their blood, then ſuch as have the ſame blood, though corrupted in their vaines, and none more eager fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of their barbarous cuſtomes, then ſuch as have had the good fortune and miſery at once to know better, and were bred up with all poſſible care in our Schooles and Univerſities, and in the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion: Nay, ſo farre has the corruption proceeded, that many of thoſe Commanders that were ſent from hence, have turned their backs to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and have been made the inſtruments to undoe and ruine them, for whoſe ſakes, they were employed into that Kingdome; (as if the whole earth had the property that ſome of its waters have, to turne all that is caſt into it, into ſtone.) By this time, I beleeve, it will be ſo farre from ſeeming impoſſible, that the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> ſhould follow thoſe courſes, that it will not in any meaſure ſeem ſtrange, ſince the very <hi>Engliſh</hi> themſelves, who have wanted thoſe allurements of blood and friendſhip, temptations which could never be out of the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> ſight, have been made ſupporters to the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> for whoſe deſtruction they were ſent thither.</p>
            <p>For what other part concerning the E. of <hi>Ormonds</hi> religion, though there might be much ſaid of that ſubject, touching the gentleneſſe &amp; moderation of it (if it were my intention to meddle w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> his perſon) I ſhall only ſay thus much, That it was the greateſt misfortune to the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> that he made profeſſion of the ſame religion w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> them, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very well how little he would have been able to do for his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men, had he not put on ſheeps cloathing: By this meanes he was a thiefe within the houſe, and had the keyes committed into his hand to diſpoſe of all at his pleaſure: not to hold you long, I ſhall give you this ſhort, but trueſt character of him. He is one whoſe heart has been as red in the blood of the Proteſtants, as any of his Country mens hands; without whom the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in that Kingdome might have been in a condition, not onely to have cleered all at home, but alſo to have required you here: whereas by the trechery of this man htey have been betrayed into that miſery, which at this day makes them the objects of pitty in all, but ſuch as have aſſiſted in his cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and reſolve ſtill to lay more and more weight upon them, till they have caſt them downe, never to riſe againe; which they will not faile to compaſſe, if God doe not ſpeedily put to his almighty hand and make him fall into the pit which he has digged ſo deep for them.</p>
            <p>I have knowne you too long <hi>Decius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Civilis.</note> to think you would ſay any thing but on very good grounds, eſpecially in a buſineſſe of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where the honour and life of any is concerned; for (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:117186:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>you Sir) if what you ſay be true, as upon the confidence I have in you, I ſhall ſuſpend my beliefe of any thing I have heard to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; he deſerved ſo little the thoughts of the Parliament to accept of him, ſhould he now at laſt ſubmit to them, that were I to be one of his Judges, I ſhould not be able to ſatisfie my conſcience in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of the duty I owe both to my Country and Religion, did I not give my vote to make him the ſevereſt example for after Ages, to judge the greatneſſe and hainouſneſſe of his treaſon by. I deſire for our better ſatisfaction, that you would be pleaſed to give us the knowledge of ſome particulars concerning him, that being convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced our ſelves, we may be able upon occaſion to ſtop the mouths of ſuch as open them in his commendation.</p>
            <p>Seeing I ſhall have my ſhare in the pleaſure of your Relation,<note place="margin">Marcus.</note> I ſhould in no wiſe deſerve it, did I not adde my prayers to thoſe of my friend <hi>Civilis,</hi> that you would be pleaſed to proceed in it, though I think my deſires will be but ſuperfluous; the ſubject (being ſuch as concernes the good of the Publick, wherof I beleeve you ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently carefull) being argument more then enough to induce you to it: I ſhall rather trouble you with a requeſt of my owne, which I know was in <hi>Civilis</hi> his mind to have remembred you of; however his impatience till he heard you ſpeak made him omit it: But becauſe I perceive it is contrary to your diſpoſition, I ſhall be afraid to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound it to you, unleſſe <hi>Civilis</hi> alſo make uſe of his power with you to perſwade you to conſent to it.</p>
            <p>Civilis <hi>undertaking for</hi> Decius, <hi>that he ſhould conſent to whatever was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, whereof if they pleaſed, he would be judge between them.</hi> Decius <hi>and</hi> Marcus <hi>being both content to caſt themſelves upon him,</hi> Marcus <hi>continued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You remember <hi>Civilis</hi> (for we muſt ſpeak to our judge) how not long ſince, you gave a wrong judgement of the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> (I for my part may call it ſo already) and yet though the fault were yours, the blame muſt be <hi>Decius</hi> his; ſeeing his good nature (in his relation of the miſery of the Proteſtants in <hi>Ireland</hi>) forbore to name the authors of it, which if he had done, I ſuppoſe, you <hi>Civilis,</hi> had not run into that error: now to prevent the like hereafter, my deſire is, that <hi>Decius</hi> (if while he ſpeaks of the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhall draw him upon others) that he would not be ſparing of their names, that we may know and mark ſuch as have walkt diſordered<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not according to a ſtreight and juſt rule: This I ſuppoſe is but equall, which if <hi>Decius</hi> aſſent unto, he will oblige us both, if he obſerve it in his following relation.</p>
            <p>Civilis <hi>casting the cauſe upon</hi> Marcus <hi>his ſide (notwithstanding all that</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:117186:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>Decius <hi>could bring to exempt himſelfe from ſo envious a work; he having tyed himſelfe to ſubmit to what</hi> Civilis <hi>ſhould detormine, proceeded on as followes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You may judge (by my readineſſe to obey you) what power your commands have over me,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> ſeeing they unavoidably put me upon the remembrance of what I cannot think of without the greateſt anger and indignation that is poſſible; with this encouragement however, that therein I doubt not, but before I have done, you will both bear your ſhares with me; and that I may obſerve ſome kind of order in what I ſhall ſay, I will begin with the confidence the Rebels from the beginning repoſed in the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> (which were argument ſufficient to prove him falſe) and then I ſhall ſhew you how faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (if I may miſuſe that good word) he anſwered that truſt of theirs in every particular. To prove both which, I ſhall not need to ſqueeze concluſions out of conjectures or probabilities, but ſhall give you the naked fact, which ſufficiently diſcovers it ſelfe, and his own ſpeeches, and the reſults of his owne made Counſell, from the mouths of thoſe of his owne party, who were not aſhamed to publiſh what they had done in the chamber upon the houſe top.</p>
            <p>Civilis <hi>and</hi> Marcus <hi>approving of the Diviſion be had made, and the way he promiſed to take in handling of the parts, he went on in this manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt thing that I propounded to cleer to you, is the great truſt and confidence the Rebels from the beginning repoſed in him. To make good which, though there be many more then probabilities to induce a reaſonable man to beleeve he was acquainted with the firſt deſigne and plot of the Rebellion, and there be ſome (that when time ſerves) can tell what advice and conncell he gave for the execution of it; having reſolved with my ſelfe to bring nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you but what carries the light of the Sun along with it: I ſhall give you as pregnant a proofe as can be deſired.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of <hi>November</hi> next after the Rebellion brake out, the Parliament, according to the prorogation, met againe at <hi>Dublin,</hi> whither many who were chief plotters and contrivers of that bloody Treaſon, though at that time the Caſtle of <hi>Dublis,</hi> by Gods great mercy, being ſecured, they had not declared the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves; boldly reſorted the Lords of the <hi>Pale</hi> and ſome others (who were all, it is well known) the firſt in that tranſgreſſion, in whoſe heads the buſineſſe was carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed long before it came into the others hands) had the faces to come and ſit in the upper Houſe, to adviſe forſooth for the ſafety of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> whom before they had voted to deſtruction. Amongſt many other good motions, it was thought fit by the aforeſaid Houſe of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117186:11"/>Lords, the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> concurring, that the Lord <hi>Costelogh Dillon</hi> ſhould be ſent to his Majeſty into <hi>England,</hi> with ſuch propoſitions as they thought expedient for the ſetling of peace againe in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and accordingly he was diſpatched away with private Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, how he ſhould carry himſelfe, and what chiefly he was to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt on: and though the honeſt party at Counſell-board (being at that time in power) had in their Letters to Court, given a large cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of the man and his errand, and expreſſed their diſlike of both in order to his Majeſties honour and the good of the Proteſtants; being taken priſoner here after his eſcape, you may perhaps have heard how he was entertained at <hi>Oxford:</hi> but it being out of our way, I paſſe it by. The maine of his Inſtructions was to work with the King, that the quieting of the Rebellion might be left wholly to the Parliament there, and that no forces might be ſent over out of <hi>England</hi> to make the breach wider, inſtead of cloſing of it; and to compleat all, he was to procure the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> to be made Lord Licutenant of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Behold Sirs, the ſame men that would have no aſſiſtance from hence, without which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> (in all humain probability) would have periſhed, as the next thing they thought could worke to the Rebels advantage, ſue that the Earle of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond</hi> might be made Governour: And leaſt the name of a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment held at <hi>Dublin</hi> may ſtumble you, and make you beleeve theſe Lords were honeſt at that time, and at the drawing of thoſe Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions had not engaged themſelves to the Rebels party: You muſt know (after their going into Rebellion) they ſtill owned the Lord <hi>Dillon</hi> as their Agent, and it was ordered at a full Counſell of the Rebels at <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> that the profits of the ſaid Lord <hi>Dillons</hi> Lands ſhould be ſecured to him, foraſmuch as he was employed to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty by them, for the good of the Catholick Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Truly <hi>Decius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Civilis.</note> I think you have put your beſt ſtrength in the Van, for I cannot ſee what could prove your firſt poynt more cleerly, and in the laſt place, you have fully anſwered an objection I was then going to propound to you; that order of the Counſell of <hi>Kilkenny</hi> cuts on both ſides, and like <hi>Janus</hi> his face, looks two ſeverall wayes. But I wrong my friend <hi>Marcus,</hi> I pray you therefore ſay on.</p>
            <p>In <hi>January</hi> 1642.<note place="margin">Decius.</note> when the Rebels were now a formed body, and licked into a State, upon a Petition of the chiefe Lords and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Rebels ſent to the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and by him kindly tranſmitted to his Majeſty, his Majeſty did by his Letters, ſent by Maſter <hi>Thomas Bourke,</hi> an arch-papiſt and a chiefe Rebell, require the Lords Juſtices to give power to the ſaid Earle to give a meeting to the chiefeſt of the Rebels, and to ſend to his Majeſty ſuch grievances
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117186:11"/>and deſires as they ſhould think fit to preſent to him by his Lordſhips hands. Amongſt many other grievances and other goodly demands which, no doubt, you have ſeen in print (though they were kept doſe from the Juſtices and Counſell by the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi>) for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny moneths after, they were publiſhed by the Rebels in forraigne Kingdomes; and when the Book was commonly ſold amongſt us, it was not ſuffered to be anſwered, but all motions made to that purpoſe in Parliament, ſlighted by Sir <hi>Morice Eustace,</hi> Speaker of the Houſe of Commons there, an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man (to ſay no worſe of him, and one of the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> Cabinet counſell.) Amongſt many other, I ſay, ſtrange deſires, at that time, tranſmitted by the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> to his Majeſty, one was this;<note n="c" place="margin">The Rebels Remonſtrance at <hi>Trym.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>That his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty would be pleaſed to grant that they might be governed by one of their owne Nation, a man of eſtate and repute amongſt them.</hi>] This you may eaſily perceive was the ſame with the former, contained in the Lord <hi>Dillons</hi> Inſtructiions, though (his Majeſty being ſufficiently already acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with their meaning, and perhaps the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> himſelfe) the <hi>Engliſh</hi> being now more formidable, was not willing to be named as before, but his name was left to be underſtood. Upon theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the Rebels, no doubt the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> (from the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning) had ſtrong aſſurances of being made Lord Lieutenant, and that the Earle of <hi>Leicester</hi> ſhould not ſtand in his way, who was pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely long detained at Court; and having at length obtained his diſpatch, and being as farre as <hi>Chester</hi> on his way, was unexpectedly recalled; and the carriage of the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> towards the Earle of <hi>Leceister,</hi> and thoſe that belonged to him, is argument enough to prove, that he well knew he ſhould never come to any ſuper-inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency over him, to overlook or check his proceedings.</p>
            <p>I doe make haſte from this firſt poynt, becauſe the next is that that will hold me longer; and by this that you have already heard, you may eaſily judge of the truth of what I promiſed in the firſt place to prove to you, namely, the conſidence the Rebels had in him, which I may boldly ſweare, they never intended ſhould prove for the good of the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It remaines, that I declare to you, how he has not failed in poynt of gratitude to the <hi>Iriſh</hi> that relyed ſo much upon him: This gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall head will fall into ſundry particular Treaſons and miſdemea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, altogether tending to this onely end, namely, to ſave and protect his beloved Country-men from the juſt revengefull armes of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> (and that he might compaſſe that) to bring the <hi>Engliſh</hi> into that condition, that they might not be able to proſecute a war, but he glad to accept of ſuch termes of ceſſation or peace, as he and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117186:12"/>the Rebels (I am forced for diſtinction ſake to ſever them) ſhould be pleaſed to afford them; and when there ſhould be now no more uſe of the Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to bring them (with the Rebels, who from the beginning ſtill boaſted they would come over into <hi>England</hi>) to turne their ſwords againſt the Parliament here, that had imployed, payed and entruſted them: And here Sirs, I doubt not but to make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to you, that the neceſſity (we here ſo much talk of) was ſo farre from being a <hi>cauſe of that bloody ceſſation, that the Earle of</hi> Ormonds <hi>deſigne to ſecure his Country-men by that ceſſation was the onely cauſe of that neceſſity;</hi> which (notwithſtanding all his pernicious endeavours to bring it upon us) was not, by Gods mercy, ſo great, but that the Army might very well have ſubſiſted, and that the world might ſee through it, that the ſafety of the Proteſtants was onely pretended by him, when nothing but utter ruine was really intended.</p>
            <p>There was nothing had that power over me,<note place="margin">Marcus.</note> to perſwade me to a charitable opinion of that ceſſation, as the word <hi>Neceſſity;</hi> and (to confeſte ingeniouſly to you) I could not tell what to ſay, when in the Kings Declaration touching that buſineſſe, I found neceſſity ſo much complained of in the Letters from your owne Counſell, which I thought they would not have done if it had been onely fictitious, and not reall.</p>
            <p>Truly <hi>Marcus</hi> you have prevented me,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> for I was juſt then thinking of the ſame thing; thoſe Letters having (in many mens apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) done that work to the full, for which they were inſerted in that Declaration, which was the juſtification of the proceedings in that ceſſation.</p>
            <p>I ſhall anon acquaint you at lage with the occaſion of thoſe Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> onely for the preſent to remove them ſomewhat out of our way (in generall) I ſhall tell you, that part of them w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> expreſſed the diſpairing condition of the ſtate, was written alwayes, as you ſhall plainly ſee by and by, by reaſon of the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> violent ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling for it, and by the over-ruling vote of his complices at the Board, and contrary to the opinion and advice of the honeſt Party who knew the contary, and that the Army might very well have ſubſiſted by the meanes even of thoſe ſmall ſupplies ſent from hence; yea though they had been leſſe, had not the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> uſed all the art and power he could to prevent and hinder it: This Sirs, ſince I am firſt fallen upon it, I ſhall labour to cleere unto you.</p>
            <p>Civilis <hi>and</hi> Marcus <hi>expreſſing their deſire to be informed by him, be conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued his ſpeech as followes.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:117186:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> The firſt and beſt meanes that could be uſed to bring the Army to neceſſity and want, was to keep it idle at home in our own quarters; The Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> had heard of that maxime, <hi>nihil difficilius eſt quam exercitum otioſum alere;</hi> and therefore having the ſole command of the Army, he alwayes kept it in, and about the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> a place thirty or forty miles moſt wayes from any conſiderable enemy; ſo that there was at all times five or ſix thouſand men fed upon the publick ſtores of that place, who might have been ſent abroad and lived in the enemies Country; and there were ſometimes eight or nine thouſand men maintained out of the Magazine at <hi>Dublin,</hi> and moſt commonly there was victuals delivered out for more men by one third part, then were really to be found in the Towne; and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all that the honeſt party (at Counſell-board) could doe, his Lordſhip would never be brought to take a view of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to diſcover the true ſtrength of it; but when (upon the impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity of the honeſt Privy Counſellours) the men were once carried into the Field to take the right number of them, he found out an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to diſmiſſe them, and alſo the buſineſſe was diſappointed; though (which is obſervable) when upon the ceſſation he ſaw the <hi>Engliſh</hi> would expect that the Army ſhould be ſupplied by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution of the Rebels (which the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> had talkt much of, to induce the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to conſent to that ceſſation;) he of himſelf could then give ſtrict order therein, that the Rebels might not be burdened above what was neceſſary in the leaſt meaſure.</p>
            <p>This particular of keeping ſo many men continually in <hi>Dublin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Civilis.</note> I conceive is that which cannot be anſwered, if there were any poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of maintaining them abroad to doe ſervice againſt the Rebels: I deſire therefore to be ſatisfied in that poynt which is all that can be thought of to juſtifie that action.</p>
            <p>Your deſire is indeed very materiall,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> but I ſhall eaſily ſatisfie you in it; for you muſt know, the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> did this, not onely contrary to many Remonſtrances of the honeſt party at Counſell-Board (declaring the evill conſequences thereof) but alſo to the overtures and motions of ſeverall Commanders in the Army, who undertook to maintaine the Army abroad, and make them ſubſiſt upon the Rebels, if the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> would ſuffer it:<note n="d" place="margin">Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination.</note> Sir <hi>Arthur Loftus</hi> Governour of the <hi>Naas,</hi> undertook to maintaine there a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, without charge to the State, if the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> would alſo ſend him two or three Troops of horſe which lay idle about <hi>Dublin:</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Sir <hi>Charles Coot</hi> his Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination.</note> Sir <hi>Charles Coote</hi> long ſolicited the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> for a thouſand Foot and two or three Troops to carry into <hi>Conogh,</hi> where he undertook to maintaine them upon the Rebels during the Warre.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117186:13"/>And many the like propoſitions were made by others, but the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> knew too well how much it would have prejudiced his Country-men and his deſigne, to ſave them by a peace or ceſſation, to conſent to any of them; but they were all ſlighted by him, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he had ſtill the face to complaine of the neceſſity of the Army, &amp; to the great diſturbance of all debates at Counſel-board for the good of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and the promoting of the Service, to preſſe and cry continually for Letters to be writ to his Majeſty; declaring their lamentable condition, and how they were not poſſibly able to ſubſiſt, no not for a few dayes, whereby the Officers and Soulders were encouraged to all manner of mutinous diſorders, being moſt of them already wrought to a wearineſſe of the ſervice, and to a deſire to come into <hi>England</hi> to gaine the ſpoile of the ſame, whereof his Lordſhip and his inſtruments had given them aſſurance.</p>
            <p>The Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> being ſenſible of the Earl of <hi>Ormonds</hi> proceedings, and how he laboured all that he could on pretence of neceſſity, to gaine for the Rebels what they deſired, to the ruine of the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> to wipe away that colour of neceſſity, and that it might cleerly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare where the fault lay, that the Proteſtants were not in a better condition, undertook about <hi>January</hi> 1642. a deſigne for the carrying out a great part of our Army to live abroad in the Country, and doe good ſervice againſt the Rebels; the propoſition (as it deſerved) was much magnified by all, being ſo much for the good of the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> that indeed it was the onely meanes for their preſervation: The Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> upon the Lords Juſtices and honeſt Privy-Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours motion, gave conſent unto it; whereupon all things were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, Iron Mils and other neceſſaries, not without great charge, were provided, and all things being now in a readineſſe for the Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> to march: The Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> (fore-ſeeing how much this would ruine his plot, and fearing that he intended for the County of <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> a place which he alwayes kept untouched, being the chiefe ſeat of the Rebellion, where their ſupreame Counſell reſided) declared, he would goe out himſelfe in perſon, and (contrary to the will of the Juſtices, and the advice of the honeſt party at Counſell-Board, ſaying, he had power of himſelfe without them, to carry out the Army when and whither he pleaſed) he overthrew the Lord <hi>Liſles</hi> motion, having no other deſigne then to thwart his, which looked too ſeverely (he thought) upon the Rebels his beloved Country-men: Sometimes he declared he would goe into the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Wesimeath,</hi> other times into the County of <hi>Longford,</hi> but at length (having taken new Counſels, and cauſed the State to furniſh him with a treble proportion of mony to what the Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> deſired
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117186:13"/>for his expedition, which the Parliament Commiſſioners then at <hi>Dublin</hi> were forced to take up in that neceſſity upon their own word, otherwiſe he and ſome of his Minions of the Counſell of warre, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting they were the cauſe of the diſappointment of that ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a ſervice, and having upon his owne motion a generall War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant granted him from the Lords Juſtices, to command all the ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the coaſt of the whole Kingdome, a thing which before was never given out of the hands of the chiefe Governour for the time, and having a Warrant likewiſe for the putting of the whole Country, where-ever he came, to contribution; and full power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him to protect them, otherwiſe ſaying, he could not be able to keepe the Army abroad, as he pretended he would doe, for three moneths; he marched out of <hi>Dublin</hi> with about 4000. foot, and four or five hundred horſe.</p>
            <p>In their martch through the County of <hi>Kildare,</hi> they took in three or four Caſtles, namely, <hi>Timelin, Tullow</hi> and <hi>Castle-Martin,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſuch quantities of corne, as would have been ſufficient to have fed the Army three moneths; but the Earl of <hi>Ormond</hi> ſuffered it to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed and waſted, and no uſe made of it to their benefit: That which was taken in <hi>Timelin,</hi> was left moſt of it in the ſame condition it was found: and after the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> was martched away, the Rebels came and poſſeſſed themſelves againe of it, which will be made good by Colonel <hi>Monk</hi> and by the parties that ſurveyed the corne in thoſe Caſtles: By which it may appeare, he never had any intention to maintaine the Army abroad, or that he took thoſe places to any other end, then to waſte the ammunition and proviſion which he carried out with him, and which (he knew) was all the ſtore: <hi>Castle Martin,</hi> and ſome other places taken by him, being not long after ſold, and delivered up to the Rebels, and that at very low rates: <hi>Castle Martin</hi> was ſold to the Rebels by Colonel <hi>Hunkes,</hi> whoſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany had the poſſeſſion of it, and no notice taken of it by the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> in publick; but what thanks he gave in private for it, we may gueſſe (preſuming it was done by his owne order.)</p>
            <p>I cannot but admire <hi>(Decius)</hi> at what you have told me,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> ſeeing how much hitherto the Earl of <hi>Ormonds</hi> carriage diſagrees from thoſe expreſſions I have heard ſome give of him, upon whom hereafter I ſhall looke as enemies to the Common-wealth, and as ſuch as deſerve to partake in the ſevereſt of his puniſhments; and truly (by what I have already heard from you, and ſome other Relations which I have received of the carriage of the Earle of <hi>Thomond</hi> and ſome others in <hi>Munster</hi>) I begin plainly to underſtand the vanity of imploying any of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in conſiderable command in that ſervice,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117186:14"/>if we ever intend to have the work carried on throughly and faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not partially and by halves.</p>
            <p>I have ever in my owne thoughts embraced that opinion as the moſt certaine and ſafeſt vvay for the <hi>Engliſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Decius.</note> and indeed ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing there were ſuch of that Nation as could ſo farre overcome their owne natures, as willingly to undertake ſo contrary a work, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it a poynt of cruelty in man (if there were no more in it) to put humain nature to ſo hard a taske, as to embrue his hands in the blood of thoſe neereſt to him, which was thought by God a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent tryall even for ſuch a faith as <hi>Abrahams:</hi> But beſides this, I ever eſteemed it a poynt of the greateſt indiſcretion, to expoſe the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to the mercy of ſo many temptations as daily beſet ſuch men, and it being a certaine rule, that <hi>no man ever hated his owne fleſh,</hi> though ſome would be beleeved, to have attained to that perfection; but if you pleaſe to give me leave, I ſhall begin where I left off in my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</p>
            <p>Civilis <hi>praying him to doe ſo, be continued his ſpeech in this manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After the taking of thoſe Caſtles (as you have heard) the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> carried the Army before the Towne of <hi>Roſe,</hi> through a coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try which he knew could afford them nothing but ſtreights and wants, whereas if he had gone ten miles on the other hand into an open Country, he might have been in the heart of a place untouched by any enemy, where the Army might have ſubſiſted upon the Rebels as long as they pleaſed; but the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> had not for that end preſerved that Country from ſpoyle, to be now waſted; And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as before the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> advance towards <hi>Roſſe,</hi> the Rebels might have been at a loſſe, not knowing which way our Forces would bend, being equally neer <hi>Kilkenny, Wexford</hi> and <hi>Roſſe,</hi> to cleer them of that doubt, and to free them from the danger of a ſurprize, which (if the whole Army' or a party of Foot, with ſome Horſe, had ſpeedily martched up to either of thoſe places) might eaſily have been performed: He commanded the Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> with ſome Horſe, without either Foot or Dragoons, to martch before to <hi>Roſſe,</hi> which gave the Country an allarum, and the body of Foot came up ſo ſlowly after, that the Towne had time to prepare it ſelfe, and to take in more Forces; whereas if there had been Foot ſent up with the Horſe, it might without all queſtion have been taken; they within being ſo ſecure, that ſome of the Lord <hi>Liſles</hi> Horſe at their firſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found the gates wide open, whereat they entred, but for want of Voot to make it good, they were forced to retire.</p>
            <p>When the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> ſuppoſed the Rebels were prepared to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117186:14"/>receive him, the Army was brought before the Towne (though he had prepared nothing fit for a ſiege, and that it was contrary to the intention of the State, that he ſhould engage before any place of that ſtrength, till they had firſt beaten the Rebels out of the field, being ſent abroad meerly to live and maintaine themſelves, which could not but be knowne impoſſible, lying in the midſt of an enemies Country before a Towne, the Rebels having a ſtrong Army on foot to cut off all proviſion, and forrage as they pleaſed. You may remember I told you before, how that the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> before he would ſtirre out of <hi>Dublin,</hi> muſt have the command of all the ſhiping on the coaſt of the Kingdome, and (to make ſome good uſe of this power (he cals up two ſhips that lay neer the Fort of <hi>Duncannon,</hi> and on pretence to hinder ſupplies from coming to the Towne over the River from <hi>Munſter</hi> ſide, they were commanded by him into ſuch a place, that they were both taken, to the great loſſe of the owners, and the encouragement of his Country-men; and having, with the expence almoſt of all his ammunition, made a breach in the wall, wide enough for twenty men to enter a breſt, having thereby let the world ſee what he could have done, he riſes from before it, and ſets his face homewards towards <hi>Dublin,</hi> and in his way brings the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my upon the Rebels Forces, commanded be <hi>Preſton</hi> add <hi>Cullin;</hi> where if Gods mercy had not overcome his wickedneſſe, the loſſe of thoſe men had been in humain reaſon the ruine of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> through the whole Kingdome.</p>
            <p>The Rebels, contrary to their uſuall manner (being ſpurred on with other aſſurances then they could receive from their owne cowardly diſpoſitions) at this time charged very reſolutely, on our ſide the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> gave out no orders for the ordering or managing of the battle, but rid up and downe careleſly with one Colonel <hi>Barry</hi> an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſt, and one very well knowne by the Rebels, as if he had not been conterned in the buſineſſe in hand: by which meanes for want of direction, the Rebels had at firſt gotten advantage over us, which the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> had a ſpeciall care to impute to ſuch as he knew moſt forward and zealous againſt his Country-men, and particularly to the Lord <hi>Liſle,</hi> who in truth behaved himſelf: that day very gallantly, to his great honour and the advantage of the ſervice.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed God, notwithſtanding all the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> wiſhes and endeavours, to give the <hi>Engliſh</hi> the day, with the loſſe of many of the Rebels Gentry, and divers taken priſoners, amongſt whom was <hi>Cullin,</hi> their Lieutenant generall, and ſome more of their princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Officers, who were brought to <hi>Dublin</hi> in ſuch ſtate, that one
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117186:15"/>would have thought they had rid in triumph after their owne victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and not been priſoners of ours: And when the honeſt party at Counſell-board ſpoke of committing them as Traytors, the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> took it very hainouſly, and ſaid, he would be bound for them himſelfe, and the Lord Chancellour one Sir <hi>Richard Bolton,</hi> a rotten-hearted man, and one of the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> honeſt inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on all occaſions, deſired it might be conſidered how the King uſed the Parliament priſoners here, that ſo they might follow that preſident; to which the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> added, that they in <hi>England</hi> were as great Rebels as thoſe in <hi>Ireland,</hi> though Sir <hi>Henry Tich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne</hi> (another faithfull Gentleman, whom we ſhall have occaſion anon to mention more at large) upon another occaſion went a note higher, and would prove the Parliament here the worſe Rebels of the two, for theſe (ſaid he, meaning the Rebels) fight for the ſubſtance of their Religion, but the Parliament meerly for cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies.</p>
            <p>It pleaſed GOD to beſtow upon the FORCES of the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants there,<note place="margin">Marcus.</note> very many admirable Victories, and nevertheleſſe (which ſeemed very ſtrange to us, not knowing to what cauſe to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute it) the affaires of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were (ſo far as I could underſtand) ſtill in the ſame condition, and not in any degree bettered, or neerer to an end.</p>
            <p>You ſay very true Sir,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> for though God had put many happy op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities into our hands, there was never any uſe made of any of them, but our Armies having beaten the Rebels abroad, were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently brought home to feed upon, and indeed devoure our ſelves at home: I know Sirs, you expect a fter this laſt victory to heare of a purſuit, but the E. of <hi>Ormond</hi> had a care not to break his old cuſtome; whereas if he had purſued this defeat, as a Generall ought, and an honeſt man would have done, he might have gone either back againe to <hi>Roſſe</hi> or to <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> and had either or both delivered unto him, or at leaſt he might have commanded the open field, and maintained the Army upon the country without danger as long as he pleaſed: The Lord <hi>Eſmond</hi> (after the battle) offering to bring the Army into the old <hi>Engliſh</hi> Baronies neer <hi>Wexford,</hi> a place plentifully ſtored with corne and cattle, and all manner of proviſion for them to ſubſiſt on: The motion was rejected by the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and as if he had undertaken this, as a journey onely to viſit ſome friends, within a little more then three weeks he returnes to <hi>Dublin;</hi> the money he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for this expedition (beſides what he had in proviſion) being ſufficient to have fed that proportion of men in Towne for three moneths; and leaſt the honeſt party at counſell-board might have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117186:15"/>diſpoſed otherwiſe of thoſe Forces, he never gave the State notice of his intentions till the Army was far advanced into our owne Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and were come within ſome few miles of the City, and then he writ, that he could not keep the men abroad any longer unleſſe he had proviſions ſent to him, but never ſtayed for an anſwer; ſo that before what proviſions were to be gotten could be diſpatched away to him, he was come with the men to the Town's end; and this he did when he knew there was not three dayes ſubſiſtence for them in the ſtores, but they were all billeted upon the City; of which burden the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Papiſts had the leaſt ſhare: by the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> Order many able <hi>Iriſh</hi> in and about the City being wholly ſpared, and their load laid upon the ſhoulders of the poore <hi>Engliſh</hi> families, who had hardly bread for their owne mouths, but they muſt be brought to the extreameſt miſery that was poſſible, that they might be the better fitted and prepared willingly to accept of whatſoever he ſhould be pleaſed to doe with them: and notwithſtanding all this, none ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more ſenſible of the miſery of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> then himſelfe: the burden of his ſong was continually, <hi>Neceſſity, Neceſſity,</hi> that the Parliament had utterly forſaken us, and converted the money raiſed for us to their owne uſes, and that it behooved us to provide what way we could for our owne ſafeties, ſince it was impoſſible any longer to hold out a warre: All his work at Counſell-board was, to cry like the two daughters of the Horſe leech, <hi>Give, Give,</hi> and to preſſe the Counſell to write diſpairing Letters to his Majeſty, that ſo his Majeſty might have grounds to command him to conclude a Ceſſation (as his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty has ſince made uſe of thoſe Letters to juſtifie himſelfe therein (as you <hi>Marcus</hi> obſerved very righty in the beginning.)</p>
            <p>I had almoſt forgot one paſſage which fals in with this place, and may be worth your hearing. The Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> having notice (after the Battle) that one of our Souldiers (being taken by the Rebels upon quarter) was afterwards in cold blood hanged by them, deſired the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> (to terrifie them from committing the like villany upon the reſt, if peradventure they had or ſhould have any more in their hands) that ſome of their men taken by us at that time, might be uſed in the ſame manner: To which the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully replyed, that if they were barbarours, he would not be barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous too: Upon this confidence that the Rebels had in the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> (though there were many more priſoners of theirs in our power, then they had of ours, which might have made them hold their hands) they never failed to execute the worſt of their cruelties, Captaine <hi>Bret</hi> taken by the Rebels, after quarter given, was in cold blood ſhot to death by them; Captaine <hi>Chambers,</hi> taken neer <hi>Carelowe</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:117186:16"/>upon quarter, was afterwards delivered by <hi>Preſton</hi> to one <hi>Harpoole</hi> at <hi>Kilkenny,</hi> and by him moſt barbarouſly murdered; one young Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net to the Lord <hi>Liſle</hi> taken neer <hi>Dublin</hi> (after long impriſonment) was afterwards hanged; Captaine <hi>Treſwell</hi> (who commanded the Lord <hi>Liſles</hi> Troop) petitioned the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> for reparation for <hi>Young,</hi> and an examination upon oath concerning Captaine <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> of the inhumain cruelties executed upon him, was preſented to the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> and he moved to require ſatisfaction, but his Lordſhip was angry, and nothing was done in either; and yet though his Lordſhip were ſo much out of love with that barbarous vertue of juſtice, he delighted as much on the other ſide in mercy, and therefore when there was a plot diſcovered, that a whole company of <hi>Iriſh</hi> men conſpired together to runne from their Garriſon at <hi>Rings End</hi> to the Rebels, and but one of them was picked out to ſuffer for example (the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> being unwilling that any one ſhould dye for ſo good a work, whileſt he had power to hinder it,) he was reprieved by him, and afterwards ſaved, and an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Cutler in <hi>Dublin</hi> being condemned for furniſhing the Rebels with armes, was by the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> earneſt ſolicitation afterwards acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and there are ſo many other particular inſtances of his affection to ſpare his Country-men, that (having ſo many things to acquaint you with after this taſte that I have already given you) to repeat them would be as unneceſſary as tedious to you.</p>
            <p>After this that you have already told us,<note place="margin">Civilis.</note> I doe not ſee what can be further added to make his diſaffection and naughtineſſe more evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, you have given us in this one buſineſſe of the diſappointment of the Lord <hi>Liſles</hi> propoſition, and the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> purſuit of it; ſo compleat a ſeries and chain of miſchief, that I cannot tell how you will be able to adde one link to it.</p>
            <p>What you have heard,<note place="margin">Decius.</note> is but a piece of one Act, one ſcene onely of that Tragedy which to this day is ours, but in the end (I doubt not) but will prove the authors, if our ſinnes doe not keep back his puniſhment.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding theſe and many ſuch like carriages of the Earle of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and what might have been apprehended by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of greateſt diſaffection in them; ſuch was their zeale to the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and their preſervation of the remaining <hi>Engliſh</hi> there, and ſo much care did they expreſſe therin, as in the very height of the diſtempers of this Kingdome, when all was little enough for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and though they ſaw how much of the proviſions made for <hi>Ireland</hi> was intercepted in its way thither (as at <hi>Cheſter</hi> and other places) they continued ſtill doing good to us, and furniſhed us,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117186:16"/>though not ſo plentifully as was deſired, yet (conſidering their condition) in ſuch meaſure, as we had no cauſe to complaine of them, or deſpaire of our ſelves; if there had been that uſe made of thoſe ſupplies as might have been, had not the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred it, who (by this goodneſſe of the Parliament towards the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants) was ſo farre from being raiſen to the leaſt joy or thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that it was the griefe of his ſoule, that (by ſhewing any care of us) they put back the work he had in hand to our ruine; and therefore he uſed all meanes that could be invented to waſte and ſquander away what we received from them, and ſo to diſoblige them, that for the future they might be drawne to deſiſt from ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any more money or proviſions to an army they ſaw ſo adverſe to them.</p>
            <p>About the beginning of <hi>July</hi> 1643. Captaine <hi>Thomas Bartlet</hi> was ſent into <hi>Ireland</hi> with his Ship laden with corne and other proviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and another Ship ſtored with three hundred barrels of powder and a great proportion of match; both which arrived at <hi>Dublin</hi> about two moneths before the ceſſation; at which time the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> thought the <hi>Engliſh</hi> were reduced to ſuch neceſſity, that it was impoſſible for them to ſubſiſt without the ceſſation; but by the arrivall of this ſupply, finding himſelfe diſappointed, he was not a little troubled, but he ſoon found out a way to piece his work up againe; and to empty the ſtores once more (as he had done often be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to as little purpoſe) he pretends a journey in all haſte towards <hi>Caſtle Jordon,</hi> and thereupon hurries up to <hi>Dublin</hi> moſt of the For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that were garriſoned in <hi>Drogheda,</hi> alias, <hi>Tredagh, Trym</hi> and <hi>Don<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalke,</hi> where they remained feeding upon the ſtores of that place ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny dayes before his Lordſhip could be ready to martch out; and having at length ſent out the Lord <hi>Lambert</hi> before him with a party of the Army (who either through the Earle of <hi>Ormonds</hi> command or his owne cowardize, durſt not advance further then twelve miles from the City, but kept his men there, feeding upon what they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried abroad with them;) he himſelfe at laſt martched out to him, his whole ſtrength conſiſting of about five thouſand, beſides Horſe and a great traine of Artillery; and having kept the men abroad till they had conſumed their proviſion, he brought them home againe, without doing any manner of ſervice againſt the Rebels, onely he took in an ordinary dwelling houſe, unfortified, poſſeſſed by ſome fevv of the Rebels: yet before his Lordſhip could be ready to martch out and doe theſe brave exploits, all the money that could be raked from the Exciſe, and what could be torne from the poor <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and almoſt all the proviſion that Captaine <hi>Bartlet</hi> had brought in was
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117186:17"/>conſumed; and of what remained, part was privately ſold to ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Bakers and others in the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and part concealed and removed into private Granaries till after the ceſſation, that it might not appeare to hinder it,<note place="margin">Sir <hi>Philip Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civel</hi> was Com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſary of the Victuals in <hi>Ireland</hi> at that time. Sir <hi>Philip Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civel</hi> was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as Clarke or Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to write all the paſſages at the making of the ceſſation on the Lord of <hi>Ormonds</hi> part.</note> and then ſome of it was ſold, and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney converted to private uſes, and the reſt, inſtead of being uſefull to ſend out the Army to fight againſt the Rebels, was made into Biſquet, to victuall the Regiments ſent into <hi>England</hi> (to fight againſt the Parliament) in Captaine <hi>Weaks</hi> Ships: The wayes the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> took to conſume our proviſions to no purpoſe, were ſo many and ſo apparent, that the Parliament Commiſſioners then at <hi>Dublin</hi> were bold to tell him plainly, That were the Parliament Maſters of the wealth of the <hi>Indies,</hi> as things were carried there, it would be all ſpent, and yet the <hi>Engliſh</hi> not any thing the better for it. By this taſte that I have already given you, you may ſee how he laboured all that he could to conſume what was ſent from hence, or to diſpoſe of it ſo, that it might not ſtand in the way between him and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne, for the preſervation of his Country-men, by neceſſitating the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to accept of his ceſſation or peace.</p>
            <p>The next thing which I ſhall labour to cleere to you, is the courſe the Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> took to alienate the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> from ſending any more ſupplies to us, knowing to how little purpoſe it would be, to dry up the water in the ſtreames, unleſſe he could ſtop it at the ſpring-head: But I beleeve this will be a work to overcome your patience, having (I preſume) wearied it alrerdy.</p>
            <p>Civilis <hi>and</hi> Marcus <hi>proteſting they received the greateſt contentment and ſatisfaction in hearing of him, he went on in this manner.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Earle of <hi>Ormond</hi> having been very ſuccesfull in the firſt part of his game, and drawne us to the bottome, bethinks himſelfe at the ſame time, how to free himſelfe of the Parliament, whom he found more forward to aſſiſt us, then would ſtand with the work he had in hand, and therefore labours to diſoblige them ſo, that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> being left wholly to themſelves, he might the eaſier make his hand of them. From hence aroſe thoſe many reviling ſpeeches utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by himſelfe and his inſtruments upon all occaſions againſt this Parliament and Kingdome: himſelfe alwayes having a ſpeciall care not onely to equall them with his Country-men, but to put the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament above them (as if the Rebellion and Maſſacre there were a buſineſſe to be excuſed in compariſon of their proceedings here) ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that thoſe fought onely (at the worſt) againſt his Majeſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, but theſe againſt his perſon, and that the Parliament here was the cauſe of all the miſery of that Kingdom; and therefore in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample <gap reason="missing" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1… pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
